Truman Bartlett Douglass Papers
Truman Bartlett Douglass Papers
1930-1969
Douglass, Truman Bartlett.
14 linear ft.
Papers of the American Congregational clergyman (1901-1969) concerned with urban ministry, civil rights, and Christian unity. Collection includes correspondence; sermons; records of the Board of Home Missions of the Congregational and Christian churches, later the United Church Board for Homeland Ministries (1936-1969), and the Consultation on Church Union (1962-1969); memorabilia, including awards, clippings, photographs, and the Douglass-Bartlett family genealogy; and writings.
148949
Biographical History
Truman Bartlett Douglass (1901-1969) was an American Congregational clergyman, particularly active in urban ministry, civil rights, and Christian unity. He attended Pomona College, Columbia University, and Union Theological Seminary, and was instrumental in the merger forming the United Church of Christ in 1957.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Truman Bartlett Douglass Papers consists of correspondence, sermons, church records, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing. The five folders in box 1 retain the titled separators which came with the papers (e.g., "Letters re Illness"). Additional correspondence is located in the church records series. Notable correspondents include Liston Pope, A. Whitney Griswold, Helmar A. Melum, Henry P. Van Dusen, Howard Schomer, A. Dale Freis, Cesar A. Chavez (circular, reproduction), Ralph A. Dugan (White House assistant), Hubert Humphrey, Nathaniel M. Guptill, Herbert Stroup, Constantinos Doxiades, Louis Finkelstein, Ralph W. Sockman, and Albert H. van den Heuvel.
Sermons date from the 1930s to the 1960s; roughly 75 percent were written during the first decade of Douglass' ministry. Earlier sermons are enclosed in envelopes with the title, date and parish, while later sermons are on 4x6" file cards organized by subject.
Church records relate to Douglass' work in urban ministry, civil rights, and church unity during his tenure as Executive Vice-President of the Board of Home Missions of the Congregational and Christian Churches, later called the United Church Board for Homeland Ministries. Also included are papers relating to a Child Development Group in Mississippi (CDGM), of which Douglass was chair of the Executive Committee. This material includes two handwritten signed letters from Hubert Humphrey.
Memorabilia contains clippings, photographs, speaking itineraries, and the contents of a binder of personal, biographical and travel papers. There are also sermons and manuscripts of Douglass' father, Truman Orville Douglass, Jr.; an autobiography of Emery Sargent Bartlett, Douglass' maternal grandfather; and a brief genealogy of the Bartlett and Douglass families.
Writings includes poems, prayers, unpublished books, essays, articles, pamphlets, contributions to anthologies, and other formats.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged as received. Sermons are arranged either chronologically (earlier ones) or by subject (later ones), as received. Church records are arranged alphabetically by the organization to which they pertain, and within that roughly chronologically. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by the name of the person to whom it pertains. Writings are subdivided by type and then arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
See also the
Truman Bartlett Douglass Booklet
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; Church and clergy; Bartlett family -- Genealogy.; Douglass family -- Genealogy.; Douglass, Truman Bartlett.; Congregational churches -- Clergy.; Consultation on Church Union.; United Church Board for Homeland Ministries.; Christian union -- United States.; City clergy -- United States.; Civil rights -- Religious aspects -- Christianity.; Clergy -- United States.; Congregationalism.; Congregationalists -- United States.; Annual reports.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Genealogies (histories); Photographs.; Reports.; Sermons.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Truman Bartlett Douglass 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - A-Z (Box 1)
- Sermons
  - Earlier, by date (Box 2-16)
  - Later, by subject (Box 17-18)
- Church records
  - Board of Home Missions of the Congregational and Christian Churches
    - Reports of principal officers of the Board, in General Council, 1936-1968 (Box 19)
    - Reports of T. B. Douglass, Executive Vice President, 1946-1968 (Box 20)
    - Addresses of T. B. Douglass, in General Council, 1936-1964; 2 audiotapes (Box 21)
    - Annual reports, 1943-1944 (Box 21)
    - Biennial reports, 1943-1944; 1947-1958,; 1960-1961; 6 folders (Box 21)
  - United Church Board for Homeland Ministries (UCBHM)
    - Biennial reports, 1962-1969 (Box 22)
    - Organizational assignments, correspondence, memoranda, report file (Box 22)
    - Printed material, pamphlets and brochures (Box 22)
    - Child development group in Mississippi (CDGM), correspondence (including two letters from Hubert Humphrey), press releases, printed material (Box 22)
  - Consultation on Church Union (COCU)
    - Reports, 1966-1969 (Box 23)
    - Proceedings, 1962-1967; 5 volumes (Box 23)
- Memorabilia
  - Bartlett, Emery Sargent, autobiography, manuscript (Box 23)
  - Douglass, Truman Bartlett
    - Awards and citations (Box 23)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 23)
    - Photographs (Box 23)
    - Speaking engagements (Box 24)
    - Personal and biographical material (Box 24)
    - Travel (Box 24)
  - Douglas, Truman Orville, Jr.
    - Miscelleneous (Box 24)
    - Sermons (Box 24)
  - Douglass-Bartlett families (Box 24)
- Writings
  - Miscellaneous
    - Poems, prayers, essays (Box 25)
  - Unpublished material
    - Books
      - The Church (Box 25)
      - Worship (Box 25)
    - Articles and essays
      - By title, A-P (Box 26)
      - By title, R-Y (Box 27)
  - Published material
    - Pamphlets and separates (Box 27)
    - Books
      - Mission to American (1951) (Box 28)
      - Preaching and the New Reformation (1956) (Box 28)
      - Why Go To Church? (1957) (Box 28)
  - With others
    - The New World of Urban Man (1965), with Constantinos Doxiades (Box 28)
  - In anthologies
    - The Witness of the Churches of the Congregational Order (1940) (Box 28)
    - Crisis in the Church, edited by E. C. Parker (1968) (Box 28)
    - Great Phrases of the Christian Language (1958) (Box 28)
    - The Prospects of Christianity Throughout the World, edited by M.. Searle and Wilhelm Pauck (Box 28)